A Guide to the Chris Burnside Papers, 1981-2009, undated
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
The Chris Burnside Papers, 1981-2009, undated
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 393
2 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The materials were placed on loan to Special Collections and Archives in 2009 by Chris Burnside.
Biographical Information
Chris Burnside is a choreographer, performer, and a former dance professor at Virginia Commonwealth University. He has a BFA in Communication Arts and Design from VCU and an MM in Dance from Florida State University. His dance and performance work ranges from complete choreography to movement monologues. He has performed in New York City, Los Angeles, Washington, D.C., and several other locations along the East Coast. For a more detailed look at his decision to move from New York City to Richmond to teach at VCU and his successful and varied career as an openly gay performer and professor, see “A Brief Narrative” by Chris Burnside in this collection.
Scope and Content
These papers document Chris Burnside’s performances, which span from 1981 to 2009. It primarily includes reproductions of the articles and the digitized performances, which were digitized from various media storage formats by VCU Libraries. The material was placed on loan by Chris Burnside. The original media formats were returned to him after digitization by VCU Libraries. Other materials include flyers, posters, promotional pamphlets, exhibition books, and correspondence. Of particular note are the items that relate to the Grace Street Theater’s restoration from the Lee Art Theater and the event that coincided with its reopening, for which Burnside composed a benediction.
Burnside studied dance under Richard Carlyon and performed in his honor at VCU event. His papers include an invitational pamphlet and articles about the event. Outside of the Chris Burnside Papers, Special Collections and Archives houses the exhibition catalog for Richard Carlyon: A Retrospective in book collection stacks under the call number N 6512 .C37 A4 2009.
Arrangement
The Chris Burnside Papers are arranged in four series. The series arrangement is as follows:
Series 1: Performances, 1984-2009
This series includes specific performances in which Burnside participated and choreographed. The arrangement of this series reflects the lender’s original order. The folders are primarily in alphabetical order by performance/event name and then in chronological order if the event shares its name. Some of the dances were performed or were written about in the press over multiple years, but all materials related to a specific dance are placed together. Items in this series include flyers, publications, announcements, reviews, and other materials associated with each performance.
Series 2: Other materials, 1981-2009
This series consists of materials that fit into the wider scope of his career and life as they relate to dance, performance, and other activities. The folders are in alphabetical order and include a reflective biographical essay, a paper about the future of dance, and other articles and reviews.
Series 3: Digitized performances, undated
This series consists of digitally captured performances spanning the years of the collection. Each file is named for the title of the performance in alphabetical order followed by a number denoting different versions of the same performance. The digital content is stored on a Lacie Grand external hard drive.
Series 4: Oversized Posters, 1988-2007
This series includes the oversized posters stored in the flat files. They are arranged in alphabetical order.
Contents List
- Performances, 1988-2009, undated (Box 1)
  Alphabetical followed by chronological
  - 1708 Gallery Performance, 1986 December-1987 January (Box-folder 1:1)
  - A Queer Kind of Night, 1995 August (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Artists for Life, 1988 May-June, 2007 January, undated (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Artists for Life 2, 1991 September, undated (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Becoming the Man, 1986 January (Box-folder 1:5)
  - ‘body/language’, 1990 May-June (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Chris Burnside and Dancers, 1988 March-April (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Chris Burnside and Dancers, 1989 July (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Chris Burnside and Dancers, 1991 May, undated (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Chris Burnside and Dancers, 1991 June (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Chris Burnside and Dancers, 2003 August-September (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Chris Burnside at P.S. 122, undated (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Diamonds on the Soles of Their Shoes, 1986 November (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Fast Forward, 1987 August-September, undated (Box-folder 1:14)
  - For Africa Benefit, 2007 November (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Fort Head, 1992 September-1995 January, undated (Box-folder 1:16)
  - May Repertory, 1997 April-May (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Richard Carlyon: A Retrospective, 2009 September (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Runaway Horses, 1989 November, 1992 November, 1995 May, 2004 April, undated (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Setting Sun, 1994 September, undated (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Travelogue, 1999 June-August, 2000 February-October, 2001 August (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Unexpected Images, 1989 February (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Work by Two Friends, 1984 February-July (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Yes, Virginia Dance!, 1999 May (Box-folder 1:24)
- Other Materials 1981-2009, undated (Box 1)
  - A Brief Narrative by Chris Burnside, 2009 Dec 17 (Box-folder 2:25)
  - Grace Street Theater restoration materials, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 2:26)
  - Technique: Futures for Dance, a paper presented to the National Association of Schools of Dance, 1998 September (Box-folder 2:27)
  - Miscellaneous Announcements and Reviews, 1981-2004 (Box-folder 2:28)
  - Miscellaneous Feature Articles, 1986-1996, undated (Box-folder 2:29)
- Digitized Performances undated
  Alphabetical
  - 2 On a Party undated
  - Andante undated
  - Artists for Life undated
  - At the Edge of Thira undated
  - Das Buch Der Tranen undated
  - Dithyramb undated
  - Drink Me undated
  - En La Noche Mi Boca Es Muy Roya undated
  - Fallout undated
  - For Africa Benefit undated
  - Fort Head undated
  - M undated
  - Narcissus & Goldmund undated
  - Oh Lucy undated
  - Out Of the Wall undated
  - Parisifal undated
  - Rhetoric undated
  - Richard Carlyon’s MOVE Concert undated
  - Runaway Horses undated
  - Sacrifice undated
  - Shared Peaches undated
  - Silver Rain Fell undated
  - Stone From the River undated
  - Styx undated
  - The Chair undated
  - The Great Wall undated
  - The Jump undated
  - To Bleed Willingly and Joyfully undated
  - Travelogue undated
  - Understanding undated
- Oversized Posters, 1988-2007 (Folder 4:30)
  - Artists for Life, 1988 May 20-21 (Folder 4:30)
  - Chris Burnside and Dancers, 2003 September 5-13 (Folder 4:30)
  - Chris Burnside and Dancers, 1991 May 10 (Folder 4:30)
  - For Africa, 2007 November 1-3 (Folder 4:30)